Finding Aid for Richard Crawford (1935- )Papers, 1893-1915, 1949-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Richard Crawford (1935- )papers 1893-1915, 1949-2001
Crawford, Richard (1935- )
3.75 linear feet
89164 Aa 2
Professor at University of Michigan School of Music, papers largely related to the Music School's Honors Program and Crawford's teaching career.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated to the Bentley Library by Prof. Richard Crawford (# 7472 ) in August 1987. Later accessions from 1996 and 2003 have been added to the collection.
The record group is open without restriction.
Richard Crawford received his collegiate education in music entirely at the University of Michigan and spent his professional career on the UM faculty. Crawford received his bachelor's degree from UM in 1958, a master's in music in 1959, and a doctorate in musicology in 1965. He joined the University of Michigan faculty in 1961, becoming an assistant professor in 1966, associate professor in 1969, and full professor in 1975.
Crawford's research interests focus on American music, with particular emphasis on the eighteenth and nineteenth century. His volume William Billings of Boston (co-written with David P. McKay) won the American Musicological Society's Kinkeldey Award in 1976, while The Core Repertory of Early American Psalmody won the Sonneck Society's Lowens award in 1986.
The Crawford papers in the main date from 1949 to 2001. Historical material collected by Crawford dates from 1893 to 1915. The Crawford papers measure 3.75 linear feet. They consist almost exclusively of records from the School of Music's Honors Program, which Crawford administered in the 1960s, and Crawford's teaching material. The collection has been divided into four series, School of Music Records, Teaching Material, Other Professional Material, and Collected Historical Music Material.
Subjects:
Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan Jazz Band.; University of Michigan--Bands.; University of Michigan. School of Music.; Moore, Earl Vincent, 1890-1987.; Howland, William.; Musicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Music--Michigan--Detroit.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Amphitheaters.; Concerts.; University of Michigan Jazz Band.; University of Michigan--Bands.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- School of Music Records
  The School of Music Records, 1958-1988 (.75 linear feet) date from 1958 to 1988. They consist primarily of Honors Program material, from the program's founding in 1958 through the late 1960s. Included are general administrative records and a number of student papers. In addition to the Honors Program records, the School of Music subgroup contains information regarding the UM Jazz Band tour of Central and South America in 1965. Included are newspaper clippings and published reviews of concerts from Central and South American newspapers, programs and photographs. Crawford served as the Jazz Band's faculty advisor during the academic year that the tour was made.
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes 1982-1988 (Box 1)
  - Honors Program
    - General Administrative Records
      - 1958-1961 (Box 1)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 1)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 1)
      - 1964-1965 (Box 1)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 1)
      - 1966-1967 (Box 1)
      - 1967-1968 (Box 1)
      - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - Forms (Box 1)
    - Recitals (Box 1)
    - Seminar Papers, Music at Michigan (Box 1)
  - General Material
    - Bicentennial Committee 1974 (Box 1)
    - Honors Assembly 1962-1967 (Box 1)
    - Jazz Band Tour 1965-1966, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Music Literature Course Change 1966 (Box 1)
- Teaching Material
  Crawford's Teaching Material, 1959-2001 (2.25 linear feet) is arranged in three series, Course Material, Reference File (by name), and Reference File (by date). Course Material is arranged by course number and includes syllabi, tests, and handouts, and occasionally lecture and background notes. The documentation for Music 450 is rich, particularly the lecture materials, which run about 1.0 linear foot. The lecture materials are arranged by title and contain lecture notes and handouts for any number of years, from the late 1980s to the late 1990s. Other documentation of a similar but less comprehensive nature has not been retained. Music 450 serves as an exemplar or Crawford's lecture and teaching style, and was chosen for its comprehensiveness, its upper-level nature, and for the frequency with which Crawford taught the course.
  The Reference File (by name) is an alphabetically arranged file of lecture material and background notes arranged either by composer name or subject. The reference file (by date) is identical in content to the name reference file, but is arranged chronologically by century. While the three series are distinct files, they work together as an intellectual whole. Notes on a particular composer or musical style apparently were used by Crawford in more than one of his courses, with the level of detail and emphasis varying in terms of the specific characteristics of each course.
  - Course material
    - Course 42 (Box 1)
    - Course 121 (Box 1)
    - Course 125 1959-1961 (Box 1)
    - Course 129 1963 (Box 1)
    - Course 131 1985 (Box 1)
    - Courses 139-140 1962-1964, 1990-1995 (Box 1)
    - Course 177 1960-1962 (Box 1)
    - Course 178 (Box 1)
    - Course 239 1966 (Box 1)
    - Course 240 1967 (Box 1)
    - Course 241 1949 (Box 1)
    - Course 295-296 1965-1969 (Box 2)
    - Course 343 (Box 2)
    - Course 396-397, Honors Seminar
      - 1961-1963 (Box 2)
      - 1964-1968 (Box 2)
    - Course 412 1963 (Box 2)
    - Course 442 1988, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Course 450
      - Course Outlines and Exams 1961, 1966-1971, 1978-1992, 2001 (Box 2)
      - Coursepack
        - 1988 (Box 2)
        - 1990 (Box 2)
        - 1996 (Box 2)
      - General 1961-1970 (Box 2)
      - Lecture Materials, ca. 1988-2001
        - 1940s and 1950s-Generalizations (Box 2)
        - 20th Century Music-Overview (Box 2)
        - Advent of the Professional Musician in America (Box 2)
        - American Music and Its Two Written Traditions (Box 2)
        - American Music and the Common Man (Box 2)
        - Bands and Band Music (Box 2)
        - Billings (William) of Boston (Box 2)
        - Blues (Box 2)
        - Composers and Their Audiences (Box 2)
        - Copland, Aaron (Box 2)
        - Cosmopolitan and Provincial: The Historiography of American Music (Box 2)
        - Course Introduction (Box 2)
        - Duke Ellington and His Orchestra (Box 2)
        - Economies of Music (Box 2)
        - Final Lecture (Box 2)
        - Foster, Stephen (Box 2)
        - Gershwin, George (Box 2)
        - Heinrich and Gottschalk (Box 2)
        - I Got Rhythm (Box 2)
        - Ives' Music, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Jazz Age and the Avant-Garde (Box 2)
        - Jazz Misc., 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Mason, Lowell (Box 2)
        - Music from the Other Side of the Tracks (Box 2)
        - Pluralism in American Music After World War II (Box 2)
        - Post-Modern Era (Box 2)
        - Ragtime (Box 2)
        - Root (G.F.) and American Vocal Music (Box 2)
        - Sacred Harp, The (Box 2)
        - Secular Music in Early America (Box 2)
        - Sheet Music and the Categories (Box 2)
        - Singers and Songs (Box 2)
        - Songs of Tin Pan Alley and Broadway (Box 2)
        - Sousa and MacDowell (Box 2)
        - "Taste" and Home Music-Making (Box 2)
  - Reference File (by name)
    - Afro-American (Box 3)
    - American, 8 folders (Box 3)
    - Ars Nova, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Bach, Brandenburg Concertos (Box 3)
    - Baroque Opera (Box 3)
    - Boston Academics (Box 3)
    - Cage, John (Box 3)
    - Cooke, The Language of Music (Box 3)
    - Counter-reformation (Box 3)
    - Couperin (Box 3)
    - Electronic Music (Box 3)
    - English 470 (Box 3)
    - Fidelio (Box 3)
    - French Opera (Box 3)
    - Gottschalk (Box 3)
    - Gregorian Chant, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Handel (Box 3)
    - Haydn (Box 3)
    - Haydn & Mozart (Box 3)
    - Ives, Charles (Box 3)
    - Hymnody (Box 3)
    - Law, Andrew (Box 3)
    - Liturgical Music (Box 3)
    - Lutheran Music (Box 3)
    - Lyon, Urania (Box 3)
    - Lyricism & Italianism in the Elizabethan Madrigal (Box 3)
    - Mass Ordinary (Box 3)
    - Medieval Music (Box 3)
    - Middle Ages, Secular Music (Box 3)
    - Monteverdi (Box 3)
    - Mozart (Box 3)
    - Organ (Box 3)
    - Post-Gregorian Developments in Chants (Box 3)
    - Pre-Baroque Instrumental Music (Box 3)
    - Pre-Christian Music (Box 3)
    - Pre-Gregorian Music (Box 3)
    - Renaissance, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Romantic Viewpoints in the Arts (Box 3)
    - Romanticism (Box 3)
    - Sachs, Primitive and Medieval Music (Box 3)
    - Scarlatti, D. (Box 3)
    - Schoenberg (Box 3)
    - Swan (Box 3)
    - Thomas, Theodore (Box 3)
    - Tuning (Box 3)
  - Reference File (by date)
    - 19th Century (Box 3)
    - 20th Century, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - 1800-Present, Study Guide (Box 3)
- Other Professional Materials
  - Correspondence 1975-1980, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Lecture -- "Make a Joyful Noise," given at American Antiquarian Society 1989 (Box 4)
  - Notes and Coursework at Michigan, ca. 1959, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Collected Historical Music Material
  The Other Professional Material series (.25 linear feet) includes documentation related to Crawford's career, outside of the realm of teaching. Contained in this series is correspondence, a fair portion of which is with Earl V. Moore; the text of a lecture given to the American Antiquarian Society, and Crawford's own notes from his undergraduate courses at the university.
  - Earl V. Moore Interviews 1979, 17 audiocassettes (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Michigan Music Programs 1910-1915 (Box 4)
  - Photograph, Cast of Mikado, Detroit Conservatory of Music, 1909 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbooks
    The final series in the collection, Collected Historical Music Material, 1893-1915 and 1979 (.50 linear feet), includes materials that Crawford collected throughout his career, documenting musical history of both the university and the state. Of particular interest are the scrapbooks documenting the career of William Howland, a vocalist from Ann Arbor, and another documenting musical programs in Detroit. The latter contains programs from individual recitals, Detroit churches, concerts of the Detroit Conservatory of Music, concerts of the Detroit Orchestral Association, and the like. Also of note are Crawford's cassette tapes of interviews with Earl V. Moore, former dean of the School of Music.
    - Musical Programs in Detroit 1909-1914 (Box 4)
    - William Howland 1893-1913 (Box 4)
  - Sinfonia, publication of Phi Mu Alpha, 1910, 1913 (Box 4)
  - Transcription 1887-1889 School of Music Catalog and Ledger (Enrollment) (Box 4)